A Guide to the The Woman's Club of Loudoun, Inc., 1944-2002
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
The Woman's Club of Loudoun, Inc. 1944-2002
Thomas Balch Library
M 024
3 cu. ft., 3 oversized items
The collection contains the records of The Woman's Club of Loudoun, Inc. It includes histories, minutes, financial records, newsletters, and scrapbooks. There is a small amount of correspondence and some publications, both club produced and from other organizations.
The Woman's Club of Loudoun, Inc.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Woman's Club of Loudoun, Inc., Loudoun County, VA
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2004.0086
Historical Information
A group of thirteen women met on 19 Jul 1944 at the home of Mrs. J. Shenton (Frances Billings) Lodge (ca. 1894) to discuss forming a club and joining the Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs (hereafter VFWC). VFWC, founded in 1907, served as a way to connect women's clubs in the state so that members could draw on one another's experience and promote civic works. The attendees of the first meeting worked with the VFWC to establish the club's objectives and structure.
The first meeting of The Woman's Club of Loudoun took place on 9 Sep 1944, and 55 women joined. A Board of Governors was appointed, and Mrs. Lodge elected as the club's first president. Acceptance of The Loudoun Woman's Club into the VFWC was announced at a meeting held 4 Nov 1944. In 1946, the club adopted the iris as its flower, and purple and gold as the club's colors. The club was incorporated in 1948. The Woman's Club of Loudoun, Inc. sponsored the creation of Junior Woman's Club of Loudoun in 1950, and over the years included it in activities and fundraisers. Membership in The Woman's Club peaked in 1954 at 142 and declined in the following decades. However, in 2004 the club was recognized at the District Meeting for its recruiting efforts, with a membership standing at 59.
The club created seven departments to guide their activities: American Home, Fine Arts, Education, Citizenship, Welfare, War Service, and Red Cross. Over time some departments were added or eliminated, reflecting the changing interests of the club. Department chairmen developed a variety of programs and invited speakers to come to club events. Speakers ranged from a representative from the Norwegian Embassy to Luther H. Evans, Librarian of Congress. While many programs were for club members only, other events included guests and spouses, such as the annual picnic. Four committees were also formed at the first meeting: Hospitality, Publicity, Membership, and Registrar.
From the beginning, the arts were a strong area of interest. A music committee was established early in the history of the club, and music was an important part of its activities and programs. Programs included performances and talks by club members, as well as guest artists. The Arts Department sponsored art and writing contests in the local schools from 1945 through the 1960's, presenting awards at their annual meeting. Club members entered their own work in contests at the district meeting, which sent winners to the VFWC annual meetings. Local contests were started in 1969. The Arts Department also held workshops, organized tours, and brought in speakers.
In addition to enrichment activities for members, the club has lent support to the community. Overseen by the Ways and Means Committee, the club engaged in a variety of fundraising activities, such as card parties, fashion shows, bake sales and rummage sales to finance civic projects. From early on education and youth welfare have been of great interest to the club. The Education Department created a Student Loan Fund in 1945, intended to help students who wanted to have a teaching career. Other areas of interest include health and welfare, conservation, and community improvement projects.
Scope and Content
The collection contains the records of The Woman's Club of Loudoun, Inc. It includes histories, minutes, financial records, newsletters, and scrapbooks. There is a small amount of correspondence and some publications, both club produced and from other organizations.
Club histories were originally kept in three-ring binders, and have been filed in parts due to size. Minutes include board and general meetings. Some volumes contained inserted material such as correspondence, programs, and financial reports. Minutes were also originally in three-ring binders, and because of size have been broken down into smaller parts for filing. The 1986-1990 minutes, unlike others, were arranged in reverse chronological order. The 1996-2000 minutes include treasurer's and annual reports. There is also a duplicate set of minutes kept by Mrs. Arthur S. (Pearl Shreve) Jenkins (24 Sep 1891-14 Jul 1978), president from 1948-1951. These contain many inserts such as correspondence, notes, and newspaper clippings.
The collection also contains four scrapbooks. Two are scrapbooks put together by club presidents, which include photographs, cards, mementos, programs, and newspaper clippings. Two additional Club Scrapbooks contain correspondence, clippings, and reports. These two books are in very fragile condition.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Northington, Etta Belle Walker. A History of the Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs, 1907-1957. Richmond: Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs, 1957.
Other Finding Aid
None
Related Material
Northington, Etta Belle Walker. A History of the Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs, 1907-1957. Richmond: Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs, 1957. VREF367.9755.
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Histories - Volume 1 (part 1 of 2), 1944-1960
  - Histories - Volume 1 (part 2 of 2), 1960-1970
  - Histories - Volume 2 (part 1 of 3), 1970-1980
  - Histories - Volume 2 (part 2 of 3), 1980-1988
  - Histories - Volume 2 (part 3 of 3), 1988-2000
  - Histories - "A History of the Woman's Club of Loudoun, Inc. V.F.W.C. and G.F.W.C, 1944-2004", ca. 2004
  - Yearbooks, 1946-1949
  - Yearbooks, 1949-1951
  - Yearbooks, 1951-1954
  - Yearbooks, 1954-1957
  - Yearbooks, 1957-1960
  - Yearbooks, 1960-1962
  - Yearbooks, 1962-1965
  - Yearbooks, 1965-1968
  - Yearbooks, 1972-1975
- (Box 2)
  - Yearbooks, 1978-1983
  - Yearbooks, 1991-1992, 1997-1998
  - Certificate of Incorporation and Articles of Amendment, 1948, 1950, 1953, 1957
  - Constitution ,ca. 1948
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1969, n.d.
  - Standing Rules, Jan 1954
  - Minutes (part 1 of 3), Jan 1944-Dec 1945
  - Minutes (part 2 of 3), Jan 1946-Dec 1949
  - Minutes (part 3 of 3), Oct 1947-Jun 1950, Sep 1951
  - Minutes (part 1 of 3), Sep 1950-Dec 1951
  - Minutes (part 2 of 3), Jan 1952-Dec 1953
  - Minutes (part 3 of 3), Jan 1954-Jun 1955, Feb 1957
  - Minutes (part 1 of 3), Aug 1955-Dec 1956, n.d.
  - Minutes (part 2 of 3), Jan 1957-Dec 1958
  - Minutes (part 3 of 3), Jan 1959-Apr1961
- (Box 3)
  - Minutes (General Meeting), 3 Nov 1962
  - Minutes (part 1 of 2), Jun 1968-Nov 1970
  - Minutes (part 2 of 2), Jan 1971-Jan 1974
  - Minutes (part 1 of 2), Feb 1974- Dec 1975
  - Minutes (part 2 of 2), Jan 1976-Mar 1978
  - Minutes (part 1 of 3), Mar 1978-Dec 1980
  - Minutes (part 2 of 3), Jan 1981-Mar 1984
  - Minutes (part 3 of 3), 1982-Jan 1984, n.d.
  - Minutes (part 1 of 4), Jan 1989-Mar 1990
  - Minutes (part 2 of 4), Jan-Dec 1988
  - Minutes (part 3 of 4), Jan-Dec 1987
  - Minutes (part 4 of 4), Mar-Dec 1986
  - Minutes (part 1 of 3), Mar 1990-Mar 1992
- (Box 4)
  - Minutes (part 2 of 3), Apr 1992-Mar 1994
  - Minutes (part 3 of 3), Apr 1994-Mar 1996
  - Minutes (part 1 of 2), Apr 1996-Mar 1998
  - Minutes (part 2 of 2), Apr 1996-Mar 1998
  - Minutes (part 1 of 3), 1998-2000
  - Minutes (part 2 of 3), 1998-2000
  - Minutes (part 3 of 3), 1998-2000
  - Minutes (part 1 of 2), Mar 1990-Dec 1991
  - Minutes (part 2 of 2), Jan 1992-May 1993
  - Minutes - Duplicates (part 1 of 4), 1944-1948, 1960
  - Minutes - Duplicates (part 2 of 4), 1948-1950
  - Minutes - Duplicates (part 3 of 4), 1949-1950
  - Minutes - Duplicates (part 4 of 4), 1949-1951
- (Box 5)
  - President's Records - delegate's pin, VFWC convention, 1-Apr-61
  - President's Records - Hecht Company Consumer Advisory Board members, Jan, Jul 1953
  - President's Records - Report of President, 2 Jun 1951
  - President's Records - Report to VFWC, 1983-2000
  - Secretary's Records - Minutes (part 1 of 5), 1998-2000
  - Secretary's Records - Treasurer's Report (part 2 of 5), 1998-2000
  - Secretary's Records - District Meeting Handouts (part 3 of 5), 1998-2000
  - Secretary's Records - Miscellaneous (part 4 of 5) (see also OM 0004, Folder 1), 1998-2000
  - Secretary's Records - Newsletters (part 5 of 5), 1998-2000
  - Custodian's Records - Property Report ,ca.1954
  - Financial Records - Treasurer's Reports, 1949-May 1953
  - Financial Records - Treasurer's Reports, Aug 1954-1956
  - Financial Records - Treasurer's Reports, 1956-1958
  - Financial Records - Treasurer's Reports, 1959-1960
  - Financial Records - Treasurer's Reports, 1961-1962
  - Financial Records - Treasurer's Reports, 1963-1964
  - Financial Records - Treasurer's Reports, 1965-1966
  - Financial Records - Treasurer's Reports (see also OM 0004, Folder 2), 1981-1984
  - Financial Records - Treasurer's Reports, 1986-1988
  - Financial Records - Treasurer's Reports, 1990-1992
  - Financial Records - Treasurer's Reports, 1993-1996
  - Financial Records - Receipts and Statements, 1982-1984, 1986-1988
  - Financial Records - Student Loan Fund, 1946, 1954
  - Financial Records - Student Loan Fund Passbook, 1965-1983
- (Box 6)
  - Financial Records - Journal, 1951-1953
  - Financial Records - Journal, 1952-1953
  - Financial Records - Journal, 1953-1954
  - Financial Records - Journal, 1954-1959
  - Financial Records - Journal, 1961-1970
  - Financial Records - Journal, 1970-1980
  - Financial Records - Journal, 1972-2000
  - Financial Records - Journal, 1980-1995
  - Registration Book, 1967-1981
- (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1951, 1955-1956, 1959
  - Correspondence, 1962-1963, 1966, 1970-1971
  - Membership - Charter Members, 27-Apr-05
  - Membership - Member Roster, n.d.
  - Membership - Officers and Chairmen, 1990-1991
  - Honors and Awards - "Build a Better Community Program" application, 24 Mar 1949
  - Honors and Awards - Certificate of Merit, VFWC, "Sponsoring Music", 30-Apr-57
  - Honors and Awards - "Women's Club of Loudoun Day", 7-Apr-89
  - Photographs, n.d.
  - Photographs - Board of Supervisors' Proclamation, 1988-1989
  - Photographs, 11-Jun-05
  - Photographs, 12-Jun-05
  - Photographs, Mar 1990
  - Newsletters, 1990, 1992-1994
  - Newsletters, 1996-1998
  - Newsletters, 1999-2001
  - Publications - "Music George Washington Knew", n.d.
  - Publications - "A Profile of the Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs", n.d.
  - Publications - "The Woman's Club of Loudoun, Inc." (flyer), n.d.
  - Publications - "Interfaith Relief Newsletter" v1. no. 2, n.d.
  - Publications - "State Song of Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs", 20-May-37
  - Publications - "A Collect for Club Women", 26-Apr-05
  - Publications - "Sixty Years of Achievement: 1890-1950, General Federation of Women's Clubs", 3-May-05
  - Publications - "Program: Fifty-Sixth Annual Convention of the Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs", 1-Apr-63
  - Publications - "Virginia Clubwomen's Anthology", 1-Aug-67
  - Publications - "Invest in Your Future, Preserve Your Past, Thomas Balch Library, 1922-1992", 14-Jun-05
  - Clippings, 1944, 1954, 1957, 1966, 1983
  - Clippings, 1990-1991, 1998, 2001, 2002, n.d.
  - Miscellaneous, 1990-1994, n.d.
- (Box 8)
  - President's Scrapbook (folders 1-66); see also OM 0004, Folder 3, 1992-1994
- (Box 9)
  - President's Scrapbook (folders 1-105), 1994-1998
- (Box 10)
  - Club Scrapbook, 1948-1949
- (Box 11)
  - Club Scrapbook, 1950-1951
- (Box OM 0004)
  - Secretary's Records (see also Box 5, Folder 8), 22-Jun-05
  - Financial Records - Treasurer's Reports (see also Box 5, Folder 18), 1981-1984
  - President's Scrapbook, pg. 40 (see also Box 8, Folder 40), 1992-1994